Finding Aid for Information Technology Division (University of Michigan) records, 1956-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Divisions 1976-1995
  - 1984-1994
    - Guidelines
      - The MTS-to-UNIX Migration Guide: Don’t Panic, The Last MTS Volume You Will Ever Need, working draft, March 1994 (Box 63)
    - Guiding Principles For the Transition From the Present MTS Computing to a Future Distributed Computing Environment, May 26, 1992
    - High Performance Computing 1993 (Box 63)
    - Historical Perspective, not dated (Box 63)
    - Host Identifiers at the University of Michigan, not dated (Box 63)
    - HyperCard Contest Winner Visual Scheduling Database, 1988 (Box 63)
      (includes Macintosh 3.5" floppy disks)
    - Idea for Server-Enhanced Workstation Environment “XLII,” 1986 (Box 63)
    - InfoDisk Development 1987-1989 (Box 63)
    - Infrastructure (authentication services, x.500) 1992 (Box 63)
    - Information Technology Architecture Committee (ITAC) 1986-1987 (Box 63)
    - Information Technology Division (ITD)
      - Customer Focus Groups for ITD Staff April 1992 (Box 63)
      - Diversity
        - Critical Incidents May-July 1988 (Box 63)
        - Education Subcommittee March-October 1988 (Box 63)
        - Facilities Training November 1988-January 1989 (Box 63)
        - Initiatives
          - 1987-1988 (Box 63)
          - 1989-1993 (Box 63)
        - Kickoff Meeting August 1988 (Box 63)
        - Panel January-May 1989 (Box 63)
        - Personal Subcommittee January-December 1988 (Box 63)
      - Project Management Meetings August 1986-August 1988 (Box 63)
      - Public Forums 1986 (Box 63)
      - Service Reductions, Restructing and Additions 1992-1994 (Box 63)
      - Strategic Plan May-November 1988 (Box 63)
      - Support of Research 1993 (Box 63)
      - Support of Twisted Pair and Fiber Ethernet September 16, 1990 (Box 63)
      - User Services
        - Coordinator’s Project Meetings 1986-1987 (Box 63)
        - Retreat May 29, 1986 (Box 63)
        - Themes, Quality Indicators and Metrics draft paper, August 23, 1993 (Box 63)
    - Information Technology General Counsel (ITGC) February 1990 (Box 63)
    - Institutional File System (IFS) Project 1990 (Box 64)
    - Instructional Computing 1992 (Box 64)
    - International Business Machines (IBM) Contract for Campus Technology Center circa 1989 (Box 64)
    - Internet Backbone Port Allocation Recommendation September 12, 1991 (Box 64)
    - Intersystem Workshop 1988 (Box 64)
    - Local Area Network 1988 (Box 64)
    - Management Expectations Training Committee 1992-1993 (Box 64)
    - Manager Expectation Task Force 1991-1992 (Box 64)
    - Martin Luther King Day 1989-1990 (Box 64)
    - Massively Parallel Processing (MPP) 1992 (Box 64)
    - Mathematica 1988-1989 (Box 64)
    - Memorandum Suggested Changes in Information Technology Division Support for Electronic Communications Services, April 2, 1988 (Box 64)
    - Merit Increase Program 1990 (Box 64)
    - Micro Group
      - Committee A Meetings and Associated Materials 1986-1987 (Box 64)
      - The Evolution of Micro Group, (written by Gavin Eadie), circa 1988 (Box 64)
      - Meeting Minutes 1985 (Box 64)
      - Microplan February 22, 1984 (Box 64)
      - Progress Report April 2, 1987 (Box 64)
      - Two-year Plan, (presented at the Micro Group Retreat Patterson Fresh Air Camp) June 27, 1986 (Box 64)
      - Quarterly Report, July to September 1986 (Box 64)
    - Microcomputer Sales Evaluation Team (MSET) 1993 (Box 64)
    - Micro Project History 1984 (Box 64)
    - Multi-Media Task Force 1993 (Box 64)
    - News clippings 1993 (Box 64)
    - NUBS and Michigan Union Supervisor Meetings 1988 (Box 64)
    - Office Configuration 1988 (Box 64)
    - Open Software Foundation (OSF) Distributed Computing Environment Overview 1993 (Box 64)
    - Papers
      - Networking in Residence Halls: Participation and Impact, November 29, 1990 (Box 64)
      - Public Microcomputer Workstations at the University of Michigan June 1985 (Box 64)
    - Performance Planning and Review Process June 1989 (Box 64)
    - Policy
      - Conditions of Use of the Resources of the Information Technology Division, November 9, 1990 (Box 64)
    - Progress Report of the Subcommittee on MicroComputer Policy October 21, 1983 (Box 64)
    - Proposals
      - Campus-Wide Information Service: A Proposal and Perspective, February 1992 (proposal for Gopher BLUE Project) (Box 64)
      - For the Implementation of a Port Locator Program (LOCATE) October 20, 1986 (Box 64)
      - For an Interactive Multi-Media Lab 1988 (Box 64)
    - Printing Issues 1992 (Box 64)
    - Public Relations 1989 (Box 64)
    - Reduction in Force (RIF) 1992-1993 (Box 64)
    - Reference Documentation
      - Total Quality 103 Resource Notebook, 1994 (Box 64)
      - Working with Messages, March 1991 (Box 64)
    - Reorganization Effort 1989
      - May (Box 65)
      - June (Box 65)
      - July (Box 65)
      - August (Box 65)
      - December (Box 65)
    - Reports
      - Advancing Educational Uses of Information Technology at the University of Michigan, September 10, 1987 (Box 65)
      - Improving the Infrastructure, draft April 15, 1992 (Box 65)
      - Non-University MTS Users: An Overview of Service Trends and Problems October 7, 1987 (Box 65)
      - Priority Services Review Perceived Value Study Report January 17, 1991 (Box 65)
      - Service/Budget Overview December 10, 1990 (Box 65)
    - Residential Computing Budget 1990-1991 (Box 65)
    - Residential Computing Leasing Computers to Students 1995 (Box 65)
    - Salary/Merit Program 1994 (Box 65)
    - Senior Management Notes 1993 (Box 65)
    - Special Interest Group in Labs (SIGLABS) Meetings 1985-1986 (Box 65)
    - Site Licensing 1987-1988 (Box 65)
    - Special Associate to the Director 1989 (Box 65)
    - Statement of Direction May 1992 (Box 65)
    - Strategic Data Plan Reference Document April 18, 1994 (Box 65)
    - Strategic Directions for Information Technology June 1989 (Box 65)
    - Study Abroad Program 1989-1991 (Box 65)
    - Symposium Making Connections: A Computing Symposium at the University of Michigan, March 30, 1989 (Box 65)
    - TULIP Status Report March 1994 (Box 65)
    - Quality Improvement Team: Managing Electronic Classrooms 1991-1992 (Box 65)
    - UNIX
      - Proposals for Unix Support
        - 1987-1988 (Box 65)
        - 1988-1989 (Box 65)
        - 1990-1992 (Box 65)
      - User’s Group 1988 (Box 65)
    - User Documentation Issues circa 1993 (Box 65)
    - USER: FORUM (Discussion on Total Quality Management) 1991 (Box 65)
    - User Services, 3.5” Floppy Disk Conversion circa 1987 (Box 65)
    - User Services Needs Assessment Project 1987 (Box 65)
    - Videotape Script for National Center for Research to Improve Postsecondary Teaching and Learning (NCRIPTAL) circa 1988 (Box 65)
    - Virus Problems 1988 (Box 65)
    - Vulnerability Policy March 1988 (Box 65)
    - Working Papers Implementation Plans 1991-1992 (Box 65)
    - Working Group Report May 1992 (Box 65)
    - Workstation Evaluation Committee 1988 (Box 65)
- Networks
  The Networks series is comprised of documentation on various local, regional, and national networks in which ITD was involved, including NSFNet and the Merit Network, Inc. The series is divided into two subseries,: 1984-1992 and 1990-1995, corresponding to two separate accessions.
  - 1984-1992
    The 1984-1992 subseries (4 linear ft.) documents the university's and ITD's participation in a number of local, regional, and national computer networking organizations, including Bitnet, CICNet (Committee on Institutional Cooperation Network), CREN (Corporation for Research and Educational Networking), Merit, MITN (Michigan Information Technology Network), NREN (National Research and Educational Network), NSFNET (National Science Foundation Network), and ONENET. The material reflects the university's participation as member, host, or manager and/or Van Houweling's service as a board member or advisor. The Merit, NSFNet, and CICNet records are the most significant. Since Merit managed the NSFNET network, researchers should note that the Merit files hold considerable material on NSFNET. Other records include Board of Directors minutes, correspondence, and a topical file. Of particular note in the topical file are drafts entitled "Merit: Michigan Universities Computer Network" and an unpublished paper on the history of Merit, 1989. There are also copies of the agreements among UM, NSF and Merit, including several grant proposals. (Note: This is not the archives of Merit, but only material collected by Van Houweling in his role as chairman of the board.) The NSFNet files include executive committee minutes and correspondence, quarterly and annual reports on the operation of the network, and speeches by Van Houweling about NSFNet. Photographs and network diagrams of Merit and NSFNet can be found in the Photographs series. The CICNet material is comprised of a single chronological file of correspondence, minutes and reports. Also included in the Networks series is material related to Project EXPRES (Experimental Research in Electronic Submission). This was a collaborative project among ITD, the College of Engineering, and other units to develop protocols and standard formats for electronic submission and exchange of journal articles between dissimilar environments, particularly complex, graphically intense subjects in science and engineering. The records include a grant proposal, correspondence, reports, and publicity material, 1987 to 1989.
    - Bitnet 1987-1989, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - CICNet (Committee on Institutional Cooperation Network)
      - Correspondence, etc. 1985-1992, 19 folders (Box 9)
      - Monthly Status Reports 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - CREN (Corporation for Research and Educational Networking)
      - Board of Directors, Minutes etc. 1989-1990, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - Correspondence, etc. 1990-1991, 7 folders (Box 10)
      - NJE Position Paper (re. BITNET message system text format) (Box 10)
    - MERIT
      - Board of Directors 1987-1992, 12 folders (Box 11)
      - Correspondence, 8 folders (Box 11)
      - Topical Files
        - Historical Material
          - Aupperle Reports "Merit: Michigan's Universities' Computer Network" 1985, 1986, 1987 (Box 12)
          - Mulcahy Paper (untitled paper on history of Merit, 1989) (Box 12)
        - CICNet
          - Evaluation Team Report January 17, 1990 (Box 12)
          - Network Management and Support Proposal June 1990 (Box 12)
        - Hope College (Box 12)
        - Michnet Business Plan 1990 (Box 12)
        - NASA Connectivity Proposal 1991 (Box 12)
        - Networking Seminar May 21, 1991 (Box 12)
        - NSF-Gateway Proposal Between Merit and the Internet 1985 (Box 12)
        - NSFNet
          - Merit/UM/NSF Agreements on NSFNet 1987 (Box 12)
          - Network Management Meeting March 1988 (Box 12)
          - Grant Proposals
            - Management and Operation of the NSFNET Backbone Network 1987 (Box 12)
            - Operation and Management of the NSFNet Backbone (Supplementary Proposal) April 1990 (Box 12)
            - Implementation and Management of Improved Connectivity Between NSFNet and CAnet April 1990 (Box 12)
          - Merit/NSFNet Publicity (Box 12)
        - Valluga Announcement August 1990 (Box 12)
    - MITN (Michigan Information Technology Network) 1986-1989, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - NREN (National Research and Educational Network)
      - Correspondence, Reports, etc. 1989-1991, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - NSFNET (National Science Foundation Network)
      - Executive Committee, Minutes and Correspondence
        - 1988-1989, 5 folders (Box 12)
        - 1990-1991, 5 folders (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, misc. 1987 (Box 13)
      - NFS Service Center, "Network News" 1988 (Box 13)
      - Press Clippings 1989 (Box 13)
      - Reports (Management of NSFNET)
        - Annual Report November 1990 (Box 13)
        - Project Review May 1989 (Box 13)
        - Quarterly and Monthly Reports 1989-1991, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Van Houweling Speeches on NSFNET 1988-1989 (Box 13)
    - NYSERNET 1989 (Box 13)
    - ONENET, Strategic Plan 1989 (Box 13)
    - Project EXPRES (Experimental Research in Electronic Submission)
      - Briefing Notebook 1987 (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, Reports 1984-1987, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Grant Proposal 1986 (Box 13)
      - Publicity 1988 (Box 13)
    - University Satellite Network Project 1987 (Box 13)
  - 1990-1995
    The Networks, 1990-1995 subseries (1.5 linear ft.) includes records of the Committee for Institutional Cooperation Network (CICnet), the Corporation for Research and Educational Networking (CREN), Merit Network, Inc., and NSFNet (National Science Foundation). Records related to CICnet and CREN are more extensive in the previous subseries, but there is significant documentation for Merit and NSFNet in this accession. Since Merit managed the National Science Foundation backbone network, however, it is important to note that there is overlap between the two. There is also overlap with the records of the Computing Center record group. Included in the NSFNet files are drafts and a final version of the 1987 proposal submitted to the NSF on August 14, 1987. The files also include a transcript for the House of Representatives’ Committee on Science, Space, and Technology proceedings on March 17, 1992, during which Van Houweling reported on the enormous success of the network. His speech ideas and a draft are also in the folder. Merit files represent Van Houweling’s board participation and are not the archives of the network; files include meeting minutes, budgets, reports, proposals (all incomplete). Among the documents are a 1990 marketing plan, a strategic planning retreat in 1992, a 1990 kindergarten to grade 12 training guide, and a 1995 consultant’s report, “Analysis of Gender Bias Issues.”
    - CICNet (Committee on Institutional Cooperation Network)
      - General 1989-1995, 2 folders (Box 31)
      - Proposal to the National Science Foundation 1992 (Box 31)
      - Provost's Symposium 1995 (Box 32)
      - Resource Guide 1992 (Box 32)
    - CREN (Corporation for Research and Educational Networking) 1990-1995 (Box 32)
    - Merit Computer Network 1990-1997 (Box 32)
      (3 folders and 3 expandable folders)
    - NSFNet (National Science Foundation)
      - General 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box 32)
      - Executive Committee 1992-1993 (Box 32)
        (includes Office of Inspector General Review)
      - Proposal 1987 (Box 32)
      - Proposal 1993 (Box 32)
      - U.S. House of Representatives 1992, 2 folders (Box 32)
- University Files
  The University Files series contains correspondence and other records which document ITDs involvement with other university-based organizations, such as the Media Union, and the Library System. The series is divided into two subseries, 1984-1992 and 1992-1997, reflecting two separate accessions.
  - 1984-1992
    The 1984-1992 subseries (2 linear ft.) consists largely of correspondence between ITD and academic and administrative units. It is divided into two subseries: Executive and Administrative Offices and Academic and Support Units. Files for individual units range from several items to several folders and provide information on the state of computing, information technology development, and unit computing applications. The records also reflect programmatic and budgetary concerns during a period of rapid change in the campus computing environment.
    - Executive and Administrative Offices
      - Regents
        - Van Houweling Presentations, 1 folders (Box 14)
          - "The Future of Information Technology at UM" 1985 (Box 14)
          - Statement before U.S. House of Representatives Committee on Small Business 1988 (Box 14)
        - General 1985-1986 (Box 14)
        - Computer Sales 1989 (Box 14)
      - President's Office 1986-1992 (Box 14)
      - Vice Provost and Chief Financial Officer 1986 (Box 14)
      - Vice President for Academic Affairs 1984-1992, 4 folders (Box 14)
      - Vice President for Business and Finance (Presentation for Womack's seminar, 1989) (Box 14)
      - Vice President for Development and Communication 1984-1992 (Box 14)
      - Vice President for Research 1985-1985 (Box 14)
      - Alumni Office (Box 14)
      - Division of Research Development and Administration 1985-1986 (Box 14)
      - Personnel Service Center (Box 14)
      - Registrar 1985 (Box 14)
      - Student Loan Operations 1985-1986 (Box 14)
    - Academic & Support Units 1984-1992
      - Architecture and Urban Planning (Box 14)
      - Art School (Box 14)
      - Business Administration, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory (CSMIL) 1985-1986 (Box 14)
      - Collegiate Institute for Values and Science 1986 (Box 14)
      - Composition and Computers Group (Box 14)
      - Continuing Education for Women (Box 14)
      - Education, School of 1985-1988 (Box 14)
      - Engineering, College of
        - 1983-1987 (Box 14)
        - 1990-1992 (Box 14)
      - English Language Institute 1985 (Box 14)
      - Global Change Project 1991-1992, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Information and Library Studies 1987-1988 (Box 14)
      - Institute for Social Research 1986 (Box 14)
      - Law School
        - General 1985-1992 (Box 14)
        - Library Automation Report 1989 (Box 14)
      - Library
        - 1984-1988 (Box 14)
        - 1990-1991 (Box 14)
      - Literature, Science and Arts 1985-1992, 3 folders (Box 15)
      - Medical Affairs
        - Hospitals 1985-1992, 4 folders (Box 15)
        - Medical School 1985-1992, 3 folders (Box 15)
        - INS (Information and Networking Services) 1991, 3 folders (Box 15)
        - ITN (Information, Technology and Networking) 1991 (Box 15)
        - ITUM 1992 (Box 15)
        - IAIMS, (Integrated Academic Information Management Systems) 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Michigan Media 1984-1985 (Box 15)
      - Music 1984-1992, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Natural Resources 1986-1991 (Box 15)
      - Near Eastern Studies 1986 (Box 15)
      - Nursing 1985-1992 (Box 15)
      - Pharmacy 1985-1992 (Box 15)
      - Population Studies Center (Box 15)
      - Public Health 1986-1991 (Box 15)
      - Rackham 1992 (Box 15)
      - Social Work 1986-1991 (Box 15)
      - Statistical Computing Unit, Review 1990 (Box 15)
      - UM-Dearborn 1989-1992 (Box 15)
      - UM-Flint 1986-1991 (Box 15)
  - 1992-1997
    The 1992-1997 University Files subseries (1.5 linear ft.) provides insight into ITD interactions with administrative and academic units on campus in the mid 1990s. The most substantial materials are for the Media Union, which before its dedication was known as ITIC (Integrated Technology Information Center), and known before that as the North Campus General Library. The records include program plans; executive meeting minutes, notes and agendas; art committee meeting minutes; and an Albert Kahn & Associates program analysis, 1989. The material documents the discussion that resulted in a program statement to integrate information technology into instruction, design and research, particularly in the areas of engineering, architecture and the creative arts. Media Union documentation is also held in the Deputy Vice-Provost for Information Technology series under ITIC. Other files of interest include Literature, Science & the Arts and the School of Natural Resources. LS&A files document the unit’s efforts in the late 1980s and early 1990s to more fully embrace computing for instruction and teaching. Included is a 1991 report entitled, “Computing in LS&A: A Long Range Plan.” The planning document spoke directly to problems the school believed needed to be addressed by and with ITD in order to accommodate the changing needs of its faculty, staff, and students. Files for the School of Natural Resources document SNR’s interest in utilizing geographic information systems.
    - Executive and Administrative Offices
      - Business and Finance 1993 (Box 33)
      - Division of Research Development and Administration 1992 (Box 33)
      - Housing Division,1992-1993 (Box 33)
      - International Affairs 1992 (Box 33)
      - Office of General Counsel 1994 (Box 33)
      - Office of the President 1994 (Box 33)
      - Office of Vice President for Research, Statistical Support Services 1993-1995 (Box 33)
    - Academic and Support Units
      - Architecture and Urban Planning 1994 (Box 33)
      - Art, Museum of 1994 (Box 33)
      - Art, School of 1995 (Box 33)
      - Dentistry 1992-1995 (Box 33)
      - Digital Library 1995 (Box 33)
      - Digital Projects Showcase 1995 (Box 33)
      - Economics 1992 (Box 33)
      - Education 1992-1995 (Box 33)
      - Engineering 1992-1993 (Box 33)
      - General 1995 (Box 33)
      - Institute for Social Research 1994 (Box 33)
      - Kinesiology 1994 (Box 33)
      - Law School 1992 (Box 33)
      - Literature, Science and the Arts 1992-1995 (Box 33)
      - Media Union
        (Formerly Integrated Technology Information Center: ITIC)
        - Academic Program Group 1995 (Box 33)
        - Art Committee 1996-1997 (Box 33)
        - Director Search 1995-1996, 1 folders (Box 52)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2029 ]
        - Executive Meetings 1994-1997, 3 folders (Box 33)
        - General 1995-1997 (Box 33)
        - Interim Report 1989 (Box 33)
        - Photographs undated (Box 33)
        - Planning 1994-1996, 2 folders (Box 33)
        - Program Analysis, Albert Kahn & Associates 1989 (Box 33)
      - Medical Center 1993 (Box 34)
      - Medical School 1994 (Box 34)
      - Music, School of 1993-1995 (Box 34)
      - Natural Resources 1992-1993 (Box 34)
      - Nursing, School of 1994-1995 (Box 34)
      - Partnerships 1993 (Box 34)
      - Pharmacy 1994 (Box 34)
      - Public Health 1995 (Box 34)
      - Rackham 1994-1995 (Box 34)
      - School of Information 1992-1993 (Box 34)
      - Social Work 1992-1993 (Box 34)
- Vendors
  The Vendors series contains materials relating to ITDs involvement with outside companies who contracted with the University. This series contains specific information on computers bought by the university and the particulars of their installation. The Vendors series is made up of three subseries, divided based on the date of the material's accession: 1984-1992, 1988-1996, and 1985-1994.
  - 1984-1992
    The 1984-1992 subseries (2.5 linear ft.) consists of ITD and Van Houweling correspondence, reports, and other material relating to computer, telecommunications, and software companies. The records document purchases, lease arrangements, and development projects with corporations such as Apple and IBM as the most significant. The correspondence and topical material in the Apple files document the close working relationship that developed between Apple and ITD in promoting the use of personal computers in education. The IBM files include correspondence and topical files for mainframe, personal computers, and networking issues. Of particular note are files on IFS (Institutional File System) development, 1985 to 1988, and the purchase and installation of the IBM 3090 computer, 1986 to 1987. Photographs of many of these IBM machines can be found in the Photographs series.
    - Amdahl (Box 16)
    - Ameritech 1991 (Box 16)
    - Apple
      - Correspondence, etc. 1984-1992, 8 folders (Box 16)
      - Topical
        - Academic Computing Awards 1986 (Box 16)
        - CITI/Apple Joint Development Projects 1987-1988 (Box 16)
        - Higher Education Executives Conference 1985 (Box 16)
        - "MAC Weekend" Truckload Sale 1986/87 (Box 16)
        - Sculley Visit 1988 (Box 16)
    - Apollo
      - 1984-1985 (Box 16)